A Guide to the American Work Horse Museum Collection, 1971-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
American Work Horse Museum Collection, 1971-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2005-013
2 boxes; 0.5 cu. ft.
Papers in the American Work Horse Museum Collection include newsletters, newspaper articles, letters, Board of Director meeting minutes, inventories, and receipts.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The American Work Horse Museum Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry "Buck" Buckardt was born October 24, 1904, and died December 25, 1996. He was born in DeKalb County, Illinois. Buckardt received his PhD in Agronomy at the University of Illinois. He married his wife, Mary, in 1937. In 1938, Dr. Buckardt took a government job in Washington, DC, to work in soil conservation. By 1947, Buckardt was employed by the U.S. Civil Service Commission in Korea. In 1950, he worked for Civil Service at the Pentagon. By January of 1956, Henry Buckardt became the Agricultural Attaché of the U.S. Embassy in Korea. In August of 1958, he and his family moved to Monte Vedeo, Uruguay, where he lived for 12 years and worked for the U.S. Embassy, again as an attaché. Throughout this time, Mary "Bucky" Buckardt worked for the American Cancer Society.
The American Work Horse Museum was conceived while the Buckardts were living in Uruguay, but, according to a 1971 letter by Buckardt, was incorporated on February 3, 1971. The museum grounds are on property purchased in Paeonian Springs, Leesburg, Virginia. Subsequently, artifacts and papers were donated to the Virginia Tech College of Agriculture and Life Sciences during the tenure of Dean Swiger (1993-2003). The American Work Horse Museum was moved and re-opened at the Virginia Horse Center in Lexington, Virginia, on September 26, 1998.
Scope and Content
The American Work Horse Museum Colleciton is largely composed of equine agricultural materials from the collection of Dr. and Mrs. Buckardt. The Buckardts donated their workhorse artifacts to the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences at Virginia Tech.
In addition to farming machinary and photographs still located at the museum in Lexington, the collection also contains newsletters from 1971 to 1981 featuring information on museum activities.
Other materials include an 1918 Army machine gun handbook, information on work horse teams, and a small collection of museum-related photographs.
American Workhose Museum: http://horsecenter.org/view.asp?id=workhorse
Virginia Horse Center: http://horsecenter.org/view.asp?id=home
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Folder contents are in chronological order.
Contents List
- Annual Meeting Agendas and Presidents' Reports, 1971-1989. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Artifacts: Sold, Donated, or Purchased. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Association of Living Historical Farms & Agricultural Museums. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Blacksmith Shop. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Board of Directors. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Buckardt, Henry L., Correspondence, 1971-1987. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Buckardt, Mary, Correspondence, 1971-1972. (Box-folder 1-7)
- Mrs. Buckardt's Transcripts, July 19, 1997. (Box-folder 1-8)
- Donors. (Box-folder 1-9)
- Films. (Box-folder 1-10)
- General Information. (Box-folder 1-11)
- Horse Pair Names. (Box-folder 1-12)
- Insurance. (Box-folder 1-13)
- Internal Revenue Service, Annual Reports, 1971-1979. (Box-folder 1-14)
- Inventory of Museum. (Box-folder 1-15)
- Invoices. (Box-folder 1-16)
- Keating, Leslie M.; Correspondence re: Harness Shop Donation, 1978-1979. (Box-folder 1-17)
- Letterhead. (Box-folder 1-18)
- Living Historical Farms Bulletins, 1971-1972. (Box-folder 1-19)
- Machine Gun Cart, Handbook, March 1918. (Box-folder 1-20)
- Magazine Articles, 1977-1982. (Box-folder 1-21)
- Maps. (Box-folder 2-1)
- Maryland Shire Horse Association. (Box-folder 2-2)
- National Geographic. (Box-folder 2-3)
- National Historical Society. (Box-folder 2-4)
- Newsletters, American Workhorse Museum (AWHM), 1971-1981. (Box-folder 2-5)
- Newsletters, AWHM, 1982-1990. (Box-folder 2-6)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1971-1998. (Box-folder 2-7)
- Nicaraguan Minister of Agriculture. (Box-folder 2-8)
- Old Print Shop Folio. (Box-folder 2-9)
- Ordance Museum (Army). (Box-folder 2-10)
- Photographs. (Box-folder 2-11)
- Scott, Fred (Bundoran Farms), 1997-1998. (Box-folder 2-12)
- Swiger, Andy, Correspondence, 1997-1998. (Box-folder 2-13)
- Taxes. (Box-folder 2-14)
- USDA—American Horse Record Association. (Box-folder 2-15)
- Virginia History and Museums Federation. (Box-folder 2-16)